<metadata xml:lang="en"><Esri><CreaDate>20130815</CreaDate><CreaTime>15185300</CreaTime><ArcGISFormat>1.0</ArcGISFormat><SyncOnce>FALSE</SyncOnce><DataProperties><lineage><Process ToolSource="c:\program files (x86)\arcgis\desktop10.1\ArcToolbox\Toolboxes\Data Management Tools.tbx\CalculateField" Date="20130815" Time="151130">CalculateField us03cp Charter11CT [Count_] VB #</Process><Process ToolSource="c:\program files (x86)\arcgis\desktop10.1\ArcToolbox\Toolboxes\Data Management Tools.tbx\CalculateField" Date="20130815" Time="151140">CalculateField us03cp Privat09CT [Count_1] VB #</Process><Process ToolSource="c:\program files (x86)\arcgis\desktop10.1\ArcToolbox\Toolboxes\Data Management Tools.tbx\CopyFeatures" Date="20130815" Time="154443">CopyFeatures C:\Workspace\SABINS\Summer2013\20112011MinnesotaCounts\Counts20112012CharterPrivate.gdb\US03_CharterPrivate_Counts20112012 G:\data_projects\SABINS\SABINS2\blockRectify\sabins_2011_2012_8_15_blockrectify_redo\Counts20112012.gdb\US03_CharterPrivate_Counts20112012 # 0 0 0</Process><Process ToolSource="c:\program files (x86)\arcgis\desktop10.1\ArcToolbox\Toolboxes\Data Management Tools.tbx\DeleteField" Date="20130820" Time="140044">DeleteField G:\data_projects\SABINS\SABINS2\blockRectify\sabins_2011_2012_8_15_blockrectify_redo\WaterErasedShapefiles\COPY__20112012_Counts_CharterPrivateSchs.gdb\US03_CharterPrivate_Counts20112012 OBJECTID_1;SUM_SUM_H7V001;NCESSCH</Process><Process ToolSource="c:\program files (x86)\arcgis\desktop10.1\ArcToolbox\Toolboxes\Analysis Tools.tbx\Erase" Date="20130820" Time="142700">Erase G:\data_projects\SABINS\SABINS2\blockRectify\sabins_2011_2012_8_15_blockrectify_redo\WaterErasedShapefiles\COPY__20112012_Counts_CharterPrivateSchs.gdb\US03_CharterPrivate_Counts20112012 C:\Users\borah\Documents\NHGIS_dev.sde\nhgis_dev.BORAH.MN_2010_water_final G:\data_projects\SABINS\SABINS2\blockRectify\sabins_2011_2012_8_15_blockrectify_redo\WaterErasedShapefiles\PY_SABINS_1112_03_US.shp #</Process><Process ToolSource="c:\program files (x86)\arcgis\desktop10.1\ArcToolbox\Toolboxes\Data Management Tools.tbx\AddField" Date="20130821" Time="080606">AddField PY_SABINS_1112_03_US series SHORT # # # # NULLABLE NON_REQUIRED #</Process><Process ToolSource="c:\program files (x86)\arcgis\desktop10.1\ArcToolbox\Toolboxes\Data Management Tools.tbx\CalculateField" Date="20130821" Time="081525">CalculateField PY_SABINS_1112_03_US series Mid( [GISJOIN],9,1 ) VB #</Process></lineage><itemProps><itemLocation><linkage Sync="TRUE">file://\\thalia.socsci.umn.edu\popgis\labpcs\data_projects\SABINS\SABINS2\blockRectify\sabins_2011_2012_8_15_blockrectify_redo\WaterErasedShapefiles\PY_SABINS_1112_03_US.shp</linkage><protocol Sync="TRUE">Local Area Network</protocol></itemLocation><itemName Sync="TRUE">PY_SABINS_1112_03_US</itemName><itemSize Sync="TRUE">10.187</itemSize><imsContentType Sync="TRUE">002</imsContentType><nativeExtBox><westBL Sync="TRUE">-91850.370800</westBL><eastBL Sync="TRUE">489296.310200</eastBL><southBL Sync="TRUE">671732.636800</southBL><northBL Sync="TRUE">1323895.001400</northBL><exTypeCode Sync="TRUE">1</exTypeCode></nativeExtBox></itemProps><coordRef><type Sync="TRUE">Projected</type><geogcsn Sync="TRUE">GCS_North_American_1983</geogcsn><csUnits Sync="TRUE">Linear Unit: Meter (1.000000)</csUnits><projcsn Sync="TRUE">USA_Contiguous_Albers_Equal_Area_Conic</projcsn><peXml Sync="TRUE">&lt;ProjectedCoordinateSystem xsi:type='typens:ProjectedCoordinateSystem' xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance' xmlns:xs='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema' xmlns:typens='http://www.esri.com/schemas/ArcGIS/10.1'&gt;&lt;WKT&gt;PROJCS[&amp;quot;USA_Contiguous_Albers_Equal_Area_Conic&amp;quot;,GEOGCS[&amp;quot;GCS_North_American_1983&amp;quot;,DATUM[&amp;quot;D_North_American_1983&amp;quot;,SPHEROID[&amp;quot;GRS_1980&amp;quot;,6378137.0,298.257222101]],PRIMEM[&amp;quot;Greenwich&amp;quot;,0.0],UNIT[&amp;quot;Degree&amp;quot;,0.0174532925199433]],PROJECTION[&amp;quot;Albers&amp;quot;],PARAMETER[&amp;quot;False_Easting&amp;quot;,0.0],PARAMETER[&amp;quot;False_Northing&amp;quot;,0.0],PARAMETER[&amp;quot;Central_Meridian&amp;quot;,-96.0],PARAMETER[&amp;quot;Standard_Parallel_1&amp;quot;,29.5],PARAMETER[&amp;quot;Standard_Parallel_2&amp;quot;,45.5],PARAMETER[&amp;quot;Latitude_Of_Origin&amp;quot;,37.5],UNIT[&amp;quot;Meter&amp;quot;,1.0],AUTHORITY[&amp;quot;ESRI&amp;quot;,102003]]&lt;/WKT&gt;&lt;XOrigin&gt;-16901100&lt;/XOrigin&gt;&lt;YOrigin&gt;-8579000&lt;/YOrigin&gt;&lt;XYScale&gt;266467840.99085236&lt;/XYScale&gt;&lt;ZOrigin&gt;-100000&lt;/ZOrigin&gt;&lt;ZScale&gt;10000&lt;/ZScale&gt;&lt;MOrigin&gt;-100000&lt;/MOrigin&gt;&lt;MScale&gt;10000&lt;/MScale&gt;&lt;XYTolerance&gt;0.001&lt;/XYTolerance&gt;&lt;ZTolerance&gt;0.001&lt;/ZTolerance&gt;&lt;MTolerance&gt;0.001&lt;/MTolerance&gt;&lt;HighPrecision&gt;true&lt;/HighPrecision&gt;&lt;WKID&gt;102003&lt;/WKID&gt;&lt;LatestWKID&gt;102003&lt;/LatestWKID&gt;&lt;/ProjectedCoordinateSystem&gt;</peXml></coordRef></DataProperties><SyncDate>20130821</SyncDate><SyncTime>13331900</SyncTime><ModDate>20130821</ModDate><ModTime>13331900</ModTime></Esri><mdLang><languageCode value="eng"/><countryCode value="USA" Sync="TRUE"></countryCode></mdLang><mdChar><CharSetCd value="004"/></mdChar><mdHrLv><ScopeCd value="005"/></mdHrLv><mdContact><rpOrgName>Minnesota Population Center</rpOrgName><rpCntInfo><cntPhone><voiceNum>612-625-7375</voiceNum></cntPhone><cntAddress addressType="postal"><delPoint>225 19th Ave S</delPoint><delPoint>50 Willey Hall</delPoint><city>Minneapolis</city><adminArea>MN</adminArea><postCode>55455</postCode><country>US</country><eMailAdd>sabins@umn.edu</eMailAdd></cntAddress></rpCntInfo><role><RoleCd value="007"/></role></mdContact><mdDateSt Sync="TRUE">20130821</mdDateSt><mdStanName>ArcGIS Metadata</mdStanName><mdStanVer>1.0</mdStanVer><distInfo><distributor><distorCont><rpOrgName>Minnesota Population Center</rpOrgName><rpCntInfo><cntPhone><voiceNum>612-625-7375</voiceNum></cntPhone><cntAddress addressType="postal"><delPoint>225 19th Ave S</delPoint><delPoint>50 Willey Hall</delPoint><city>Minneapolis</city><adminArea>MN</adminArea><postCode>55455</postCode><country>US</country><eMailAdd>sabins@umn.edu</eMailAdd></cntAddress></rpCntInfo><role><RoleCd value="005"/></role></distorCont></distributor><distTranOps><onLineSrc><linkage>http://www.sabinsdata.org</linkage></onLineSrc><transSize Sync="TRUE">10.187</transSize></distTranOps><distFormat><formatName Sync="TRUE">Shapefile</formatName></distFormat></distInfo><dataIdInfo><idCitation><resTitle Sync="TRUE">PY_SABINS_1112_03_US</resTitle><date><pubDate>2013-03-15</pubDate></date><resEd>1.0</resEd><citRespParty><rpOrgName>College of William &amp; Mary</rpOrgName><role><RoleCd value="006"/></role></citRespParty><citRespParty><rpOrgName>Minnesota Population Center</rpOrgName><role><RoleCd value="006"/></role></citRespParty><presForm><PresFormCd value="005"/></presForm><presForm><fgdcGeoform>vector digital data</fgdcGeoform></presForm></idCitation><idAbs>This polygon files contains 2011-2012 school-year data delineating school attendance boundaries by grade, where the last two characters of any file name designate a grade (i.e., 00 is Kindergarten, 01 is first grade and 12 is twelfth grade). These data were collected and processed as part SABINS data infrastructure project which was funded by a grant from the National Science Foundation (Award # SES-0927794, SES-0921279, SES-1123727) to create geography delineating school attendance boundaries for the largest school districts in the United States and for any school districts for which we could collect state-wide information from a state's Department of Education. These electronic boundary files represent version 1.0 of the SABINS data. Original source information that were used to create these boundary files were collected in two primary formats: GIS data from local school districts, county/municipal GIS offices and private consulting firms; these agencies used a wide-variety of geography to create these files (e.g., local cadastral or parcel data or digital imagery) and considerable care was taken to ensure that these original files accurately delineated the school catchment areas that a school district intended them to represent. The second type of original information collected for the project were analog data such as narrative/legal descriptions of boundaries, lists of street segments served by each school boundary or paper maps of school attendance boundaries that depicted the boundaries. The 2010 TIGER/line features (that consist of streets, hydrography, railways, etc.) were used to digitize school attendance boundaries and this was the primary source of information used to digitize analog information. This practice works well as most school attendance boundaries align with streets, railways, water bodies and similar line features included in the 2010 TIGER/line "edges" files. In those few cases in which a portion of a school attendance boundary serves both sides a street we use DOQQ imagery to estimate the property lines of parcels. The data digitized from analog maps and verbal descriptions do not conform to cadastral data (and many of the original GIS files created by school districts do not conform with cadastral or parcel data). When school attendance boundaries served both sides of a street (and thus the boundary did not follow a street center) digital imagery was used to estimate the property boundaries. All school attendance boundaries in this file are "block-rectified" to 2010 TIGER/Line blocks such that the outline of every school attendance boundary conforms to the edges of census blocks. In cases in which the original school attendance boundary intersects a block (as in cases in which a school attendance boundary serves children on both sides of a street) the school attendance boundary cannot identify specific addresses that are contained within the school attendance boundary. Block assignment to school attendance boundaries is determined by taking the centroid of each block (ensuring that the centroid is placed within the block) and then locating every block centroid within a school attendance boundary. Block centroids (that have a temporary school ID) are then linked back to every block polygon (by block STFID code), and the blocks are dissolved by the temporary school ID. Every school attendance boundary is then assigned a unique, permanent ID. These block-rectified school attendance boundaries cannot be used to identify specific addresses that are served by a school attendance boundary. The purpose of block-rectifying school attendance boundaries is to estimate population characteristics residing within school attendance boundaries by using the U.S. Census Bureau's data products (primarily the Decennial Census of Population and Housing and the American Community Survey). We account for every block within a school district by comparing the outer boundaries of contiguous districts and by referencing the 2010 TIGER/Line files delineating school districts. A school district's boundaries are verified with local school district personnel when there is a discrepancy in line work between local districts and that of the U.S. Census Bureau. In the March 2013 data release, the Minnesota Population Center and the College of William &amp; Mary have re-processed all data previously released. The re-processing was necessitated after the Minnesota Population Center finished a complete QA/QC process of the original, non-block rectified data. Staff checked the school to attendance boundary assignments, making changes and corrections when necessary. Staff also modified geography as necessary. As part of the re-processing, the MPC shifted the unique School Attendance Boundary IDs from a 27 character identifier to a 14-character uniqed ID. The MPC adopted this new unique identifier because we changed the block rectification process used in the original data release (October 2011). Instead of using a point-in-polygon search to assign census blocks to school attendance boundaries, we now use the NEAR command in ArcGIS for the assignment. We select all census blocks that belong to a particular school district, using the SDUNI, SDELMA, and SDSECA attributes from the Census Bureau, and all school attendance polygons for that same school district. Then, we use the NEAR command to assign blocks to school attendance polygons. If a census block falls outside all school attendance polygons, the NEAR command assigns the census block to the closest school attendance polygon based on Euclidean distance. This prevents us from assigning a census block to the wrong school district. The MPC added fields to each school attendance boundary which contain the counts of Private and Charter schools that fall within an attendance boundary. The IND_COINCI, SPECIAL_CA, IND_OPEN_E, and IND_MULTIP attributes have been dropped. The count of Magnet schools is unavailable because we used a preliminary version of the 2011-2012 NCES Common Core of Data. The preliminary version did not indicate whether a school was a Magnet.</idAbs><idPurp>The SABINS data project is designed to improve the quality and accessibility of educational geography and tabular data to the scholarly community by assembling tens-of-thousands of school attendance boundaries for the largest districts in the U.S. A primary goal is to integrate diverse spatial information delineating school attendance boundaries into a single, uniform, digital GIS database that will result in an original, geographically rich data set. Every school catchment area has a uniform data structure consisting of a unique identification number for each school attendance boundary, and information uniquely identifying any private, charter, or magnet school located within the neighborhood school's catchment area. This standardized identifying information will allow users to analyze thousands of geographic features collected and distributed by SABINS-saving individual researchers the necessity of collecting and organizing these data in a piece-meal fashion. A primary goal of the collecting school attendance boundaries is to estimate the characteristics of populations residing within school attendance boundaries so that academic researchers can explore a variety of topics. These data are designed to serve the academic community. These data cannot be used by realtors to determine if a house is served by a particular "neighborhood" school (and the license that users sign to obtain these data does not permit the use of these data for this purpose). Researchers who want to access to original GIS data collected for the project (or school attendance boundaries digitized by SABINS staff using 2010 TIGER/line files and digital imagery) can contact the SABINS staff at the Minnesota Population Center.</idPurp><idCredit>National Science Foundation Grant (Award # SES-0927794, SES-0921279, SES-1123727)</idCredit><idStatus><ProgCd value="001"/></idStatus><idPoC><rpOrgName>Minnesota Population Center</rpOrgName><rpCntInfo><cntPhone><voiceNum>612-625-7375</voiceNum></cntPhone><cntAddress addressType="postal"><delPoint>50 Willey Hall</delPoint><delPoint>225 19th Ave S</delPoint><city>Minneapolis</city><adminArea>MN</adminArea><postCode>55455</postCode><country>US</country><eMailAdd>sabins@umn.edu</eMailAdd></cntAddress></rpCntInfo><role><RoleCd value="007"/></role></idPoC><resMaint><maintFreq><MaintFreqCd value="008"/></maintFreq></resMaint><placeKeys><keyword>United States</keyword></placeKeys><themeKeys><keyword>school attendance areas</keyword><keyword>attendance</keyword><keyword>school attendance boundaries</keyword><keyword>school attendance zones</keyword><keyword>school catchment areas</keyword><keyword>school</keyword></themeKeys><themeKeys><keyword>boundaries</keyword><thesaName><resTitle>ISO 19115 Topic Categories</resTitle></thesaName></themeKeys><searchKeys><keyword>school attendance areas</keyword><keyword>United States</keyword><keyword>attendance</keyword><keyword>school attendance boundaries</keyword><keyword>school attendance zones</keyword><keyword>boundaries</keyword><keyword>school catchment areas</keyword><keyword>school</keyword></searchKeys><resConst><LegConsts><useLimit>See access and use constraints information.</useLimit><othConsts>All persons are granted a limited license to use these GIS data for academic and policy-related research and are not permitted to redistribute the data to a third party (in either its current or modified versions). These data cannot be used to for commercial purposes and reselling the data (or redistributing the data to persons or corporations that would resell or in any way profit from the data) is prohibited. See below for further applications and restrictions.</othConsts></LegConsts></resConst><resConst><Consts><useLimit>Appropriate uses of the data include thematic mapping in cases in which there is a one-to-one correspondence between a school attendance boundary and the school that serves that boundary. In some cases two or more schools serve a single school attendance boundary (a one boundary to many school relationship) or two or more schools provides serve a portion of a school attendance boundary (a many school to many school attendance boundary relationship) and thematic mapping is difficult in such situations. If these digital data are used in the production of a report or in the compilation of a standalone printed map, then this dataset is to be cited in the report or on the map using the source citation specified below. The following source citation should be used when citing this dataset: The College of William &amp; Mary and the Minnesota Population Center. School Attendance Boundary Information System (SABINS): Version 1.0, Minneapolis, MN: University of Minnesota 2011. Publications and research reports based on the database must cite it appropriately. Users are requested to send a copy of any publications, research reports, or educational material making use of the data or documentation. Printed matter should be sent to: David Van Riper, Minnesota Population Center, 50 Willey Hall, 225 19th Ave S, Minneapolis, MN 55455.</useLimit></Consts></resConst><spatRpType><SpatRepTypCd value="001"/></spatRpType><dataLang><languageCode value="eng"/><countryCode value="USA" Sync="TRUE"></countryCode></dataLang><tpCat><TopicCatCd value="003"/></tpCat><envirDesc Sync="TRUE">Microsoft Windows 7 Version 6.1 (Build 7601) Service Pack 1; Esri ArcGIS 10.1.1.3143</envirDesc><dataExt><geoEle><GeoBndBox><westBL>-97.247216</westBL><eastBL>-89.366369</eastBL><southBL>43.359832</southBL><northBL>49.386891</northBL></GeoBndBox></geoEle></dataExt><suppInfo>Some school attendance boundaries that exist on the periphery of a school district are extended to include census blocks such as large water polygons that cover a large water body (e.g., an ocean or great lake), desert, swamp, forest, or similarly large blocks that, based on digital imagery, do not contain a visible housing unit. This process ensures that all census blocks in a region are accounted for. This gives users the flexibility of excluding (i.e., clipping) unwanted or unpopulated census blocks from school attendance boundaries when block-level population counts are published in the 2010 census and 2010 TIGER block files.</suppInfo><dataExt><geoEle><GeoBndBox esriExtentType="search"><exTypeCode Sync="TRUE">1</exTypeCode><westBL Sync="TRUE">-97.247216</westBL><eastBL Sync="TRUE">-89.366369</eastBL><northBL Sync="TRUE">49.386891</northBL><southBL Sync="TRUE">43.359832</southBL></GeoBndBox></geoEle></dataExt></dataIdInfo><dqInfo><dqScope><scpLvl><ScopeCd value="005"/></scpLvl></dqScope><report type="DQTopConsis"><evalMethDesc>All spatial data have been reviewed to assure topological consistency and completeness. All polygons close and do not overlap. No voids exist within polygons. ArcGIS topology features classes were used to identify and fix topological errors (e.g., overlaps, voids, missing polygons) in the school attendance boundary datasets. The ArcGIS topology rules used to ensure logical consistency were "Must not overlap" and "Must not have gaps". These rules were enforced both to the final block-rectified files in the final data we distribute.</evalMethDesc></report><report type="DQConcConsis"><measDesc>All spatial data have been reviewed to assure topological consistency and completeness. All polygons close and do not overlap. No voids exist within polygons. ArcGIS topology features classes were used to identify and fix topological errors (e.g., overlaps, voids, missing polygons) in the school attendance boundary datasets. The ArcGIS topology rules used to ensure logical consistency were "Must not overlap" and "Must not have gaps". These rules were enforced both to the final block-rectified files in the final data we distribute.</measDesc></report><report type="DQCompOm"><measDesc>Version 1.0 of the school attendance boundary system contains all school attendance boundaries within a (non-random) sample of school districts throughout the United States. These boundary files are only composed of polygon features. Version 1.0 boundary files have be block rectified so that, for some school attendance boundaries that serve both sides of a street, it is not possible to identify specific housing units that a school attendance boundary serves. This only occurs along the periphery of some school attendance boundaries. The block-rectified school attendance boundaries have not been generalized. No school attendance boundaries (or portions of school attendance boundaries) overlap, no voids exist within school attendance boundaries or within districts for and every polygon has a unique code that uniquely identifies it.</measDesc></report><report type="DQQuanAttAcc"><measDesc>All primary keys (GISJOIN) in the SABINS database uniquely identify a school attendance boundary polygon. Schools attendance boundaries and the schools that serve them share a many-to-many relationship. In some cases a portion of two nearby school attendance boundaries can provide services to children who live in the "overlap" (as in an overlap of a Venn diagram) among boundaries. We treat this "overlap" as a distinct geographic object and it is assigned a unique identification code so that it does not break the topological logic of "must not overlap." The unique object can be associated with the remaining portion of a school attendance boundary via a link table with the Common Core of Data.</measDesc></report><report type="DQAbsExtPosAcc" dimension="horizontal"><measDesc>Data used to delineate the outlines of school attendance boundaries is the U.S. Census Bureau TIGER/Line 2010 files and the horizontal positional accuracy of the data can be found at: http://www.census.gov/geo/www/tiger/tgrshp2010/documentation.html. The outlines of all school attendance boundaries in this file consist of 2010 census blocks and some blocks are intersected by the original school attendance boundaries that were obtained from school districts or that were digitized by SABINS staff. Some census blocks are intersected by school attendance boundaries that provide educational services to children on both sides of a street.</measDesc></report><dataLineage><prcStep><stepDesc>Once a school district is selected for collection the school district's web site is explored to determine if any of the following information exists: a image of school attendance boundaries in the district in electronic form (e.g., a PDF image of school attendance boundaries), a narrative or legal description of the boundaries, a list of street segments served by each boundary or an "address locator" that allows those viewing the web site to determine the address served by each school in the district. If there is no information on a school district's web page that can be used to create a GIS file, SABINS staff call the local district to acquire information that would allow them to create a GIS file. SABINS staff also attempt to obtain any GIS data the district might have. In rare cases a district will refuse to provide information and a public record request is filed to obtain the data; most such requests are honored.</stepDesc></prcStep><prcStep><stepDesc>SABINS staff then generated the centroids, using the INTPLON and INTPLAT attributes, for all census blocks in a given state. The census school districts codes (unified, secondary, and elementary) were attached to each census block centroid. The census school district codes are needed for the block-rectification process.</stepDesc></prcStep><prcStep><stepDesc>Any information that is downloaded from a web page or obtained directly from a school district is recorded in a data collection database. The information that is entered into the data collection database includes (but is not limited to) the format of the source data (i.e., analog or digital and the specific format of the data), the contact information of the person who provided the data and the administrative unit in which that person works, the date the data were requested and the date the data were sent, the school year of the data.</stepDesc></prcStep><prcStep><stepDesc>Ran custom Python script to generate unique IDs and run the block rectification process. The block rectification process selects all census blocks with a particular school district code and then executes the NEAR tool to assign a GISJOIN code to each census block. If a census block centroid falls outside the extent of the Union polygon feature class, the tool assigns the GISJOIN code of the closest polygon, measure in Euclidean distance, to the centroid. The script then joins the centroid attributes back to the census block polygons. Finally, it dissolves the census blocks on the grade-specific GISJOIN values to create grade-specific school attendance boundaries. A by-product of this script is a crosswalk, or translation table, linking each school attendance boundary to the schools which provide it services.</stepDesc></prcStep><prcStep><stepDesc>A list of school districts is identified for data collection. SABINS staff processed data from the entire state of Minnesota.</stepDesc></prcStep><prcStep><stepDesc>Erased coastal water from each grade-specific feature class.</stepDesc></prcStep><prcStep><stepDesc>A personal geodatabase was created for every state or region (e.g., a metropolitan area or the greater area of metropolitan area).</stepDesc></prcStep><prcStep><stepDesc>Attach FGDC-compliant metadata to every feature class and convert the feature classes to shapefiles for distribution on the SABINS data access site.</stepDesc></prcStep><prcStep><stepDesc>For school districts that only provided a map, an online locator service, or narrative descriptions of attendance areas, SABINS staff had to create the attendance polygons using 2010 TIGER/Line features. Staff downloaded 2010 TIGER/Line "All" line shapefiles that covered the school district in question. SABINS staff select TIGER line segments (using the select feature tool) from the 2010 TIGER edges file that comprise the outer boundaries of a school attendance area. The line features that a school attendance boundary follows is determined by narrative descriptions, a list of street segments of the a map. If the entire outline of a school attendance boundary adheres to 2010 TIGER line segments, SABINS staff use the ArgGIS trace tool to digitize the boundaries. The trace tool selects every vertex in a line segment and thus school attendance boundaries use the same vertices as TIGER line segments. If a portion of a school attendance boundary does not follow a 2010 TIGER line segment digital imagery (Esri's World Imagery map service and World Transportation and World Boundaries+Places reference overlay services) is referenced to delineate that portion of a school attendance boundary. For example, if a school attendance boundary draws children from housing units on both sides of a street, the digital imagery is used to approximate the property lines on a street. In other cases, the digital imagery confirms that a line does not intersect the locations of housing units in unpopulated portions of a school district.</stepDesc></prcStep><prcStep><stepDesc>SABINS staff opened countywide line polygon coverage of 2010 TIGER/line school district boundaries in ArcGIS 9.3.1. The units and datum for this coverage were geographic (latitude/longitude), decimal degrees, and NAD 83. At this stage SABINS staff looked for inconsistencies between TIGER school district boundaries and locally-defined school district boundaries and contacted the school district to reconcile inconsistencies.</stepDesc></prcStep><prcStep><stepDesc>Once every polygon is assigned a (temporary) school name, SABINS staff use a custom ArcGIS tool to create a standard set of attribute fields in the attribute table associated with every school attendance boundary polygon. These fields include a field or fields for NCESSCH codes and school names from the NCES Common Core of Data.</stepDesc></prcStep><prcStep><stepDesc>All previous steps were performed by SABINS staff. Next, SABINS staff at the MPC then performed Quality Checking/Quality Assurance checks to fix mistakes and make modifications to the union feature class. The digital data were compared to the school district source data and the NCES Common Core of Data, and staff made edits using ArcMap 10.0 editing tools.</stepDesc></prcStep><prcStep><stepDesc>A feature dataset was created for every school district in the personal geodatabase for the region. The units and datum for this coverage were geographic coordinate system (latitude/longitude), decimal degrees, and NAD 83.</stepDesc></prcStep><prcStep><stepDesc>For school districts that provided digital GIS data, the data were imported into the feature dataset using ArcCatalog 9.3.1's import function. Districts usually provided GIS data for elementary, middle and high school attendance boundaries. Topology rules were applied to each (elementary, middle and high school) layer within a school district. The topology rules were "Must not overlap" and "Must not have gaps." ArcCatalog's Create New Topology was used to create a new topology feature class.</stepDesc></prcStep><prcStep><stepDesc>Once these fields are added every school attendance boundary is given a set of standard attributes. The CCDID field (or fields) are assigned a 12-digit NCESSCH ID from the 2010-2011 Common Core of Data. A customized tool was created to perform this task; the tool allows SABINS staff to select a single school attendance boundary record with a school name. Once this record is selected (with a single click of mouse) a drop-down menu appears that shows the name of every school in the Common Core of Data (for a particular school district). The appropriate record in the Common Core of Data is selected (i.e., the school names in the attribute field of a school attendance polygon and the Common Core of Data correspond) and the attribute table is given the 12-digit NCESSCH ID and the Common Core of Data school name. This "point-and-click" function reduces data entry errors.</stepDesc></prcStep><prcStep><stepDesc>After the elementary, middle, and high school layers for a given school district have the Common Core of Data NCESSCH codes assigned, SABINS staff create a Union feature class using ArcGIS' Union tool with a 30 feet. Often, the elementary, middle, and high school data we obtained from districts were misaligned. The Union process eliminates the slight geometric discrepencies we found in the data.</stepDesc></prcStep><prcStep><stepDesc>These process steps describe, in general, the procedures used to construct the SABINS school attendance boundaries. The production procedures vary depending on the available source materials. The original source data for school attendance boundaries in many districts were GIS files created by school districts, county GIS offices and private consulting firms. Some of these GIS files relied on parcel or cadastral data to delineate school attendance boundaries. In other districts it was not apparent what information was used to digitize school attendance boundaries and SABINS staff called school district personnel to determine the correct position of a school attendance boundary if the GIS file did not clearly indicate the street or feature that a boundary should follow. For those districts that did not have information in digital format (i.e., narrative descriptions of school attendance boundaries, a paper map of school attendance boundaries, or a list of street segments and/or addresses served by each school attendance boundaries) SABINS staff digitized the boundaries using 2010 TIGER/line files. Some school attendance boundaries that drew children from both sides and did not follow TIGER lines; in these instances, digital imagery (DOQQs) were used to estimate the property lines of houses on the side the street served by a school. The steps below describe a general case in which a paper map along with a narrative description of a school attendance boundary was used to digitize school attendance boundaries.</stepDesc></prcStep><prcStep><stepDesc>Once every school attendance boundary is now in digital format, every school attendance boundary is assigned the name or names of the schools, derived from the school district's source data, that provide education services to children who reside within the school attendance boundary polygon.</stepDesc></prcStep><prcStep><stepDesc>The grade-specific polygons are used with the magnet, charter, and private school points to count the number magnet, charter, and private schools withing an attendance boundary.</stepDesc></prcStep></dataLineage></dqInfo><spatRepInfo><VectSpatRep><geometObjs Name="PY_SABINS_1112_03_US"><geoObjTyp><GeoObjTypCd value="002" Sync="TRUE"></GeoObjTypCd></geoObjTyp><geoObjCnt Sync="TRUE">702</geoObjCnt></geometObjs><topLvl><TopoLevCd value="001" Sync="TRUE"></TopoLevCd></topLvl></VectSpatRep></spatRepInfo><eainfo><detailed Name="PY_SABINS_1112_03_US"><enttyp><enttypl Sync="TRUE">PY_SABINS_1112_03_US</enttypl><enttypt Sync="TRUE">Feature Class</enttypt><enttypc Sync="TRUE">702</enttypc></enttyp><attr><attrlabl>CENTROID_Y</attrlabl><attrdef>Y-axis geographic coordinate for the centroid of the attendance boundary</attrdef><attrdefs>SABINS</attrdefs><attalias Sync="TRUE">CENTROID_Y</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">String</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">254</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">0</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">0</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>GISJOIN</attrlabl><attrdef>Unique identifier for the school attendance boundary; used to join to tabular data and the School-to-Polygon crosswalks</attrdef><attrdefs>SABINS</attrdefs><attalias Sync="TRUE">GISJOIN</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">String</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">254</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">0</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">0</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>Shape_Leng</attrlabl><attalias Sync="TRUE">Shape_Leng</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">Double</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">19</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">0</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">0</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>CENTROID_X</attrlabl><attrdef>X-axis geographic coordinate for the centroid of the attendance boundary</attrdef><attrdefs>SABINS</attrdefs><attalias Sync="TRUE">CENTROID_X</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">String</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">254</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">0</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">0</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>series</attrlabl><attrdef>This attribute indicates whether a school attendance boundary changed between 2009-2010, 2010-2011 or 2011-2012. If the value is 0 (zero), the school attendance boundary is the same in 2009-2010, 2010-2011 and 2011-2012. Those school attendance boundaries that are unchanged will have the same GISJOIN value in the 2009-2010, 2010-2011 and 2011-2012 shapefiles. If the value is 1 (one), the school attendance boundary changed between 2009-2010 and 2010-2011, but is the same between 2010-2011 and 2011-2012. If the value is 2 (two), the school attendance boundary changed between 2010-2011 and 2011-2012, while it may or may not have changed between 2009-2010 and 2010-2011. SABINS defines a "change" as either a difference in the schools assigned to an attendance boundary or a difference in the footprint of the attendance area.</attrdef><attrdefs>SABINS</attrdefs><attalias Sync="TRUE">series</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">SmallInteger</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">4</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">4</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">0</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>SDSECA_g</attrlabl><attrdef>Secondary School District code</attrdef><attrdefs>U.S. Census Bureau</attrdefs><attalias Sync="TRUE">SDSECA_g</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">String</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">50</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">0</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">0</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>FID</attrlabl><attrdef>Internal feature number.</attrdef><attrdefs>Esri</attrdefs><attrdomv><udom>Sequential unique whole numbers that are automatically generated.</udom></attrdomv><attalias Sync="TRUE">FID</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">OID</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">4</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">0</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">0</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>Shape_area</attrlabl><attrdef>Area of feature in internal units squared.</attrdef><attrdefs>Esri</attrdefs><attrdomv><udom>Positive real numbers that are automatically generated.</udom></attrdomv><attalias Sync="TRUE">Shape_Area</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">Double</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">19</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">0</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">0</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>STATE</attrlabl><attrdef>State fips code</attrdef><attrdefs>U.S. Census Bureau</attrdefs><attalias Sync="TRUE">STATE</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">String</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">254</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">0</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">0</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>SDUNIA_g</attrlabl><attrdef>Unified School District code</attrdef><attrdefs>U.S. Census Bureau</attrdefs><attalias Sync="TRUE">SDUNIA_g</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">String</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">50</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">0</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">0</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>Privat09CT</attrlabl><attrdef>Count of private schools (2009-2010 Private School Universe Survey) that fall within the attendance boundary</attrdef><attrdefs>SABINS</attrdefs><attalias Sync="TRUE">Privat09CT</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">Double</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">19</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">0</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">0</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>SDELMA_g</attrlabl><attrdef>Elementary School District code</attrdef><attrdefs>U.S. Census Bureau</attrdefs><attalias Sync="TRUE">SDELMA_g</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">String</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">50</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">0</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">0</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>Charter11C</attrlabl><attrdef>Count of charter schools that fall within the attendance boundary.</attrdef><attrdefs>SABINS</attrdefs><attalias Sync="TRUE">Charter11C</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">Double</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">19</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">0</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">0</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>NUMSCHOOLS</attrlabl><attrdef>Number of schools that provide services to the attendance boundary</attrdef><attrdefs>SABINS</attrdefs><attalias Sync="TRUE">NUMSCHOOLS</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">SmallInteger</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">4</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">4</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">0</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>Shape</attrlabl><attrdef>Feature geometry.</attrdef><attrdefs>Esri</attrdefs><attrdomv><udom>Coordinates defining the features.</udom></attrdomv><attalias Sync="TRUE">Shape</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">Geometry</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">0</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">0</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">0</attscale></attr></detailed><overview><eaover>All grade-specific shapefiles contain the same set of attributes. This section of the metadata describe the content of some of the attributes, including a description of how they were created/calculated. The most important attribute in the shapefile is GISJOIN, which is the unique identifier for each school attendance boundary. Users may join the tabular census data to the shapefile using the GISJOIN attribute. Every GISJOIN consists of the following components: (1) "G" - forces programs to read the attribute as text; (2) a 7-character school district code from the Census Bureau; (3) a 4-character code representing the school or set of schools the provide services to an attendance polygon; (4) a 2-character code for the grade level. For the grade levels, "00" is used of Kindergarten. The NUMSCHOOLS attribute is a count of the schools that provide services to the attendance boundary. CENTROID_X and CENTROID_Y represent the coordinates of the geographic centroid for the attendance boundary. The Charter11C attribute is the count of charter schools that fall within the attendance boundary. SABINS staff selected schools from the preliminary 2011-2012 NCES Common Core of Data with a CHARTR11 attribute value = 1. A spatial join was executed to count the number of charter schools in each attendance boundary. The Privat09CT attribute is the count of private school that fall within the attendance boundary. SABINS staff used data from the 2009-2010 Private School Universe Survey and created a point shapefile from the latitude and longitude attributes. A spatial join was executed to count the number of private schools in each attendance boundary.</eaover></overview></eainfo><mdHrLvName Sync="TRUE">dataset</mdHrLvName><refSysInfo><RefSystem><refSysID><identCode code="102003" Sync="TRUE"></identCode><idCodeSpace Sync="TRUE">ESRI</idCodeSpace><idVersion Sync="TRUE">10.1.1</idVersion></refSysID></RefSystem></refSysInfo><spdoinfo><ptvctinf><esriterm Name="PY_SABINS_1112_03_US"><efeatyp Sync="TRUE">Simple</efeatyp><efeageom code="4" Sync="TRUE"></efeageom><esritopo Sync="TRUE">FALSE</esritopo><efeacnt Sync="TRUE">702</efeacnt><spindex Sync="TRUE">FALSE</spindex><linrefer Sync="TRUE">FALSE</linrefer></esriterm></ptvctinf></spdoinfo></metadata>
